<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <string-array name="advantages_name">
        <item>AIM</item>
        <item>STAMINA</item>
        <item>ROBUST</item>
        <item>BERSERK</item>
        <item>FEAR</item>
        <item>REPUTATION</item>
        <item>CONCEALMENT</item>
        <item>PEACE WITH NATURE</item>
        <item>SHORT LEGS</item>
        <item>CAVE KNOWLEDGE</item>
        <item>ELUSIVENESS</item>
        <item>ARCHER</item>
        <item>MAGICAL PARAPHERNALIA</item>
        <item>KNOWLEDGE</item>
        <item>HEAVENLY PROTECTION</item>
        <item>LEARNING</item>
        <item>LORE</item>
        <item>AURA OF POWER</item>
        <item>BARTER</item>
        <item>CLEVER</item>
        <item>HEALTH</item>
        <item>HONOR</item>
        <item>FAMILIAR</item>
        <item>DISEMBODIED</item>
        <item>EXPERIENCE</item>
        <item>TRACKING SKILLS</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="advantages_description">
        <item>Subtracts one from each die roll whenever she
rolls on the Missile Table to attack with a missile weapon.</item>
        <item>The Amazon can record and do an extra Move phase
each turn. She gets this bonus even when she is riding a horse - her
stamina includes being an excellent horsewoman.</item>
        <item>The Berserker can record and do an extra Rest phase
each day.</item>
        <item>The Berserker can play his Berserk chit to increase
his vulnerability to Tremendous for the rest of the day. Once he plays
it, it takes Tremendous harm to kill him. At Midnight he reverts to
normal.</item>
        <item>Whenever the Black Knight rolls on the Meeting Table he
rolls one die instead of two. His deadly reputation makes it easier for
him to trade and hire natives, and it makes his enemies think twice
before blocking or battling him.</item>
        <item>The Captain can record and do an extra phase
each day he is at a Dwelling (including a campfire). He must be at the
Dwelling when he starts to do the phase, not when he records it. He
can use the extra phase to do any normal activity.</item>
        <item>The Druid rolls one die instead of two each
time he makes a Hide die roll. </item>
        <item>When the Druid ends his turn, the
Warning and Sound chits in his tile do not summon monsters.
Individuals following the Druid will summon monsters normally.</item>
        <item>The Dwarf can never use sunlight phases, you rest an extra
effort asterisk per rest phase, and you can play the DUCK chit to Duck.</item>
        <item>The Dwarf rolls one die instead of two
whenever he uses the Hide table, the Meeting Table, or any Search
table when he is in a cave clearing. This gives him some powerful
advantages in the caves, somewhat offsetting his short legs.
Obviously, the Dwarf prefers to spend as much time as possible in
the caves.</item>
        <item>The Elf can record and do an extra Hide phase
each day. </item>
        <item>Rolls one die Instead of two whenever he rolls
on the Missile Table to make an attack with a bow or crossbow.</item>
        <item>The Magician can record and do
an extra Alert phase each day. This reflects the effects of the magical
implements he is carrying; the phase is best used to alert Magic chits.</item>
        <item>Subtracts one from each die he
rolls when he uses the Reading Runes table. </item>
        <item>The Demon, Winged Demon and Imp
cannot block the Pilgrim and they cannot be assigned to attack him:
he cannot lure them into attacking, and they cannot be assigned to
him randomly. He can block and attack them normally. His hirelings
are not protected and can lure and be assigned Demons and Imps. </item>
        <item>The Pilgrim rolls one die instead of two each time he
uses the Reading Runes table.
Starting Location: Inn or Chapel</item>
        <item>Rolls one die instead of two each time he rolls on the Reading Runes table.</item>
        <item>Can record and do an extra Enchant phase each turn.</item>
        <item>The Swordsman rolls one die instead of two whenever
he uses the Meeting Table during a Trade activity. Note: He gets this
advantage only during the Trade activity. He does not get it during the
Hire activity or when he rolls for battling natives.</item>
        <item>Instead of taking his turn when his Attention chit is
picked, the Swordsman chooses when he will take his turn.</item>
        <item>The White Knight can record and do an extra Rest
phase each day.</item>
        <item>The White Knight subtracts one from each die he rolls
whenever he rolls on the Meeting Table; this includes all rolls he
makes during trading, hiring and rolling to see if the natives will battle
him. His noble accomplishments and reputation make even his
enemies less likely to attack him, and all of the native groups are
likely to give him a little price break when he deals with them.</item>
        <item>The Witch has an invisible companion that can move
around the map separately and discover things for her. </item>
        <item>The Witch King must use Magic Sight.</item>
        <item>The Wizard knows the location of every hidden
path and secret passage in the Magic Realm. At the start of the game
he crosses all of the hidden paths and secret passages off of his
Discoveries list. He can use them all. </item>
        <item>The Woods Girl rolls one die instead of two
whenever she uses the Hide table, the Meeting table or any Search
table while she is in one of the six tiles labeled “Woods” (specifically,
the Deep Woods, Linden Woods, Maple Woods, Nut Woods, Oak
Woods and Pine Woods). She does not get this advantage in other
tiles, even when she is in woods clearings in those tiles</item>

    </string-array>
</resources>