<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <string-array name="spell_name">
        <item>Exorcise</item>
        <item>Make Whole</item>
        <item>Peace</item>
        <item>Small Blessing</item>
        <item>Blend into Background</item>
        <item>Fog</item>
        <item>Prophecy</item>
        <item>Stones Fly</item>
        <item>Talk to Wise Bird</item>
        <item>Witch Brew</item>
        <item>Elven Grace</item>
        <item>Faerie Lights</item>
        <item>Illusion</item>
        <item>Lost</item>
        <item>Persuade</item>
        <item>See Hidden Signs</item>
        <item>Blazing Lights</item>
        <item>Elemental Spirit</item>
        <item>Fiery Blast</item>
        <item>Hurricane Winds</item>
        <item>Lighting Bolt</item>
        <item>Roof Collapses</item>
        <item>Violent Storm</item>
        <item>Absorb Essence</item>
        <item>Ask Demon</item>
        <item>Broomstick</item>
        <item>Curse</item>
        <item>Pentangle</item>
        <item>Power of the Pit</item>
        <item>Dissolve Spell</item>
        <item>Enchant Artifact</item>
        <item>Melt into Mist</item>
        <item>Phantasm</item>
        <item>Transform</item>
        <item>Unleash Power</item>
        <item>World Fades</item>
        <item>Control Bats</item>
        <item>Peace with Nature</item>
        <item>Premonition</item>
        <item>Protection from Magic</item>
        <item>Sense Danger</item>
        <item>Bad Luck</item>
        <item>Deal with Goblins</item>
        <item>Guide Spider or Octopus</item>
        <item>Poison</item>
        <item>Remedy</item>
        <item>Whistle for Monsters</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="spell_type">
        <item>I</item>
        <item>I</item>
        <item>I</item>
        <item>I</item>
        <item>II</item>
        <item>II</item>
        <item>II</item>
        <item>II</item>
        <item>II</item>
        <item>II</item>
        <item>III</item>
        <item>III</item>
        <item>III</item>
        <item>III</item>
        <item>III</item>
        <item>III</item>
        <item>IV</item>
        <item>IV</item>
        <item>IV</item>
        <item>IV</item>
        <item>IV</item>
        <item>IV</item>
        <item>IV</item>
        <item>V</item>
        <item>V</item>
        <item>V</item>
        <item>V</item>
        <item>V</item>
        <item>V</item>
        <item>VI</item>
        <item>VI</item>
        <item>VI</item>
        <item>VI</item>
        <item>VI</item>
        <item>VI</item>
        <item>VI</item>
        <item>VII</item>
        <item>VII</item>
        <item>VII</item>
        <item>VII</item>
        <item>VII</item>
        <item>VIII</item>
        <item>VIII</item>
        <item>VIII</item>
        <item>VIII</item>
        <item>VIII</item>
        <item>VIII</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="spell_color">
        <item>WHITE</item>
        <item>WHITE</item>
        <item>WHITE</item>
        <item>WHITE</item>
        <item>GREY</item>
        <item>GREY</item>
        <item>GREY</item>
        <item>GREY</item>
        <item>GREY</item>
        <item>GREY</item>
        <item>GOLD</item>
        <item>GOLD</item>
        <item>GOLD</item>
        <item>GOLD</item>
        <item>GOLD</item>
        <item>GOLD</item>
        <item>PURPLE</item>
        <item>PURPLE</item>
        <item>PURPLE</item>
        <item>PURPLE</item>
        <item>PURPLE</item>
        <item>PURPLE</item>
        <item>PURPLE</item>
        <item>BLACK</item>
        <item>BLACK</item>
        <item>BLACK</item>
        <item>GREY</item>
        <item>BLACK</item>
        <item>BLACK</item>
        <item>PURPLE</item>
        <item>PURPLE</item>
        <item>PURPLE</item>
        <item>PURPLE</item>
        <item>PURPLE</item>
        <item>PURPLE</item>
        <item>BLACK</item>
        <item>ANY</item>
        <item>GOLD</item>
        <item>GREY</item>
        <item>GOLD</item>
        <item>PURPLE</item>
        <item>ANY</item>
        <item>BLACK</item>
        <item>GREY</item>
        <item>GREY</item>
        <item>GREY</item>
        <item>PURPLE</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="spell_target">
        <item>clearing</item>
        <item>character</item>
        <item>attacker</item>
        <item>character</item>
        <item>leader</item>
        <item>tile</item>
        <item>character</item>
        <item>multiple</item>
        <item>character</item>
        <item>magic(II,VIII)</item>
        <item>individual</item>
        <item>magic(III,VII)</item>
        <item>character,tile</item>
        <item>character,tile</item>
        <item>human group</item>
        <item>character</item>
        <item>clearing</item>
        <item>magic(IV,VI)</item>
        <item>multiple</item>
        <item>individual</item>
        <item>attacker</item>
        <item>clearing</item>
        <item>tile</item>
        <item>monster</item>
        <item>demon</item>
        <item>character</item>
        <item>character</item>
        <item>individual</item>
        <item>individual</item>
        <item>spell</item>
        <item>artifact</item>
        <item>individual</item>
        <item>character</item>
        <item>individual</item>
        <item>magic(all)</item>
        <item>character</item>
        <item>bats</item>
        <item>leader</item>
        <item>character</item>
        <item>character</item>
        <item>character</item>
        <item>character</item>
        <item>goblins</item>
        <item>spider, octopus</item>
        <item>weapon</item>
        <item>spell, curse</item>
        <item>sound</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="spell_duration">
        <item>Instant</item>
        <item>Instant</item>
        <item>Combat</item>
        <item>Instant</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Attack</item>
        <item>Instant</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Combat</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Permanent</item>
        <item>Permanent</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Attack</item>
        <item>Move</item>
        <item>Attack</item>
        <item>Attack</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Permanent</item>
        <item>Instant</item>
        <item>Move</item>
        <item>Instant</item>
        <item>Combat</item>
        <item>Instant</item>
        <item>Instant</item>
        <item>Permanent</item>
        <item>Permanent</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Permanent</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Permanent</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Permanent</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Phase</item>
        <item>Permanent</item>
        <item>Permanent</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Day</item>
        <item>Combat</item>
        <item>Instant</item>
        <item>Instant</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="spell_description">
        <!-- TYPE I -->
        <item>EXORCISE (I/WHITE), the spellcaster\'s clearing, Instant: Every Demon
and Imp in the clearing is killed. Every spell and Curse that is in effect in the
clearing or that is being cast In the clearing this round is instantly broken. All
color chits in the clearing instantly fatigue. This spell is the strongest of all,
and it nullifies and breaks all other spells.</item>
        <item>MAKE WHOLE (I/WHITE), one character, Instant: This spell activates all of
the target\'s fatigued and wounded action chits and repairs all of his damaged
armor (including his inactive armor). It affects only those chits that are
already inactive and only that armor that is already damaged - it does not
affect fatigue, wounds and damage that are inflicted during the current round
of combat. This spell\'s strength is equal to the Power of the Pit results that
affect action chits and armor (it does not conflict with the other Power of the
Pit results). Special: This spell breaks the Wither Curse on the target. <color name="blue">Note:
Make Whole does not repair the Magic chit used to cast the spell, because it
                fatigues after the spell takes effect.</color></item>
        <item> PEACE (I/WHITE), one character, native or monster, Combat: When this
spell goes into effect, it is instantly broken if its target is currently the target of
any other character or denizen. If he is not someone else\'s target, the spell
goes into effect.\n
1. If the target is a denizen, whether hired, controlled or not, it is instantly
unassigned. While the spell remains in effect, it cannot be assigned to a new
target. If it is hired or controlled, it cannot lure attackers.\n
2. If the target is a character, he takes back his Attention chit and any spell
or attack he is playing is cancelled. While the spell remains in effect, he
cannot charge or specify a target for an attack or spell. He can maneuver, run
away and do other actions. He cannot lure attackers into attacking him, but
attackers can be assigned to him randomly.\n
3. The spell is instantly broken when the bewitched target is named as the
target of a spell or attack. The spell is broken only if the target himself is
named as a target - he is not released by spells aimed at other targets, even
if the results affect him.</item>
        <item>SMALL BLESSING (I/WHITE), one character, Instant: The target character
immediately rolls the dice and consults the Wishes table. See Rule 4.6.8 and
the Wishes table for information on specific Wish results.</item>

        <!-- TYPE II -->
        <item>BLEND INTO BACKGROUND (II/GREY), one character, hired leader or
controlled monster, Day: The target can record and do an extra Hide phase
during his turn.</item>
        <item>FOG (II/GREY), the spellcaster\'s hex tile, Day: This spell prevents an
individual who is doing the Search activity from using the Peer table. The
spell affects every character, hired leader and controlled monster who is in
the target tile or who is trying to search a clearing in the target tile (he cannot
Peer into the tile from a mountain in an adjacent tile). This spell affects only
the Search activity. It does not prevent an individual from using spells or
Treasure cards to do the Peer activity in the tile.</item>
        <item>PROPHECY (II/PURPLE), one character, Day: The target character ignores
his recorded turn and chooses what to do on each phase of his turn as he
does the phase. He gets the same number of phases and types of activities
he is normally allowed, except that he can use an extra or enhanced activity
caused by a belonging as soon as he activates that belonging, whether it was
active during Birdsong or not. Only one horse per day can provide him with
extra phases - once he has used an extra phase caused by one horse, for
the rest of that day he cannot use extra phases caused by other horses. If
this spell is broken before he finishes his turn, he is instantly blocked. Note:
His hired leaders, controlled monsters, familiars, and phantasms must still do
the turns recorded for them.</item>
        <item>STONES FLY (II/GREY), any number of character(s), native(s), and/or
monster(s), Attack: This spell attacks each target like a missile weapon with
a length of 15, and it inflicts Light damage with one sharpness star. Special:
This spell always makes at least four attacks. If the spellcaster specifies one
target, all four attacks are made against that target. If he specifies two
targets, two attacks are made against each target. If he specifies three
targets, two attacks are made against the target where he put his Attention
chit, and one attack is made against each other target. If he specifies four or
more targets, one attack is made against each target. The spellcaster rolls
separately on the Missile Table for each hit.</item>
        <item>TALK TO WISE BIRD (II/GOLD), one character, Instant: The target
character immediately does a remote Peer activity. He specifies any clearing
on the map and uses the Peer table to search that clearing. </item>
        <item>WITCH’S BREW (II/GREY), any of the spellcaster\'s type II and type VIII
MAGIC chits that he chooses, Day: Each targeted Type II chit is
transformed into a Type IV chit, and each targeted Type VIII chit is
transformed into a Type Ill chit (see Rule 4.6.10c). </item>
        <!-- TYPE III -->
        <item>ELVEN GRACE (III/GOLD), one character, monster or native, Combat: If
the target is a character, this spell alters the time numbers on all of his Move
chits. The strength on each Move chit defines its time number: each Light chit
has a time of 1, each Medium chit has a time of 2, each Heavy chit has a
time of 3, and each Tremendous chit has a time of 4. If the target is a
monster or native, his size redefines the Move time on both sides of his
counter: a Light target has a move time of 1 on both sides of his counter, a
Medium target has a move time of 2, and so on. This Spell affects only move
times. It does not affect attack times, Duck chits, horses or Boots cards, and
it does not affect "Move/Fight" chits created by the Unleash Power Spell.
1. Elven Grace ignores any strength changes caused by the Belt of Strength;
it always uses the strength that is actually printed on each Move chit to define
that chit’s time number.
2. The Draught of Speed and Garb of Speed nullify Elven Grace. When the
target has one of these Treasure cards active, the card defines the time
number on each chit and the Elven Grace is ignored. </item>
        <item>FAERIE LIGHTS (III/GOLD), any of the spellcaster\'s type Ill and type VII
MAGIC chits that he chooses, Day:Each targeted Type Ill chit is
transformed into a Type II chit, and each targeted Type VII chit is transformed
into a Type VI chit (see Rule 4.6.10c).</item>
        <item>ILLUSION (III/GOLD), one character or the spellcaster\'s hex tile,
Permanent:  Each affected individual adds one to his result whenever he uses
any Search table. If the target is a tile, the spell affects every character, hired
leader, controlled monster or phantasm in that tile.</item>
        <item>LOST (III/GOLD), one character or the spellcaster\’s hex tile, Permanent: Each affected individual moves randomly whenever he uses the Move activity
to leave a clearing: instead of moving to the clearing he recorded, he must
use the Lost table to determine which adjacent clearing he moves to.
1. This spell affects an individual only when he uses the Move activity to
leave a clearing. It does not affect him when he runs out of a clearing or
when he starts a move between clearings, and it does not affect him when he
flies.
2. If the target is a tile, the spell affects every character, hired leader,
controlled monster or phantasm who starts a Move activity in any clearing on
that tile. The spell does not affect Move activities that start in other tiles. </item>
        <item>PERSUADE (III/GOLD), one native group, or all of the Giants in the
spellcaster\'s clearing, or all of the Ogres in his clearing, Day: The
spellcaster pacifies the targets. To hire them, he uses the Friendly column of
the Meeting table. Special: When this spell is cast by an Artifact or Spell
Book, the character who holds the item is the one who has pacified the
denizens. If no character holds the item, the spell is nullified.</item>
        <item>SEE HIDDEN SIGNS (III/GOLD), one character, Day: The target can record
and do one extra Search phase during his turn. </item>
        <!-- TYPE IV -->
        <item>BLAZING LIGHT (IV/PURPLE), cave clearing, Day: The spellcaster must be
in a cave clearing to cast this spell, and his target is that clearing. Each
character, hired leader or controlled monster in that clearing during Birdsong
has the option to record an extra phase to do any normal activity. He must
also be in the clearing when he starts the phase or the activity is cancelled.</item>
        <item>ELEMENTAL SPIRIT (IV/PURPLE), any of the spellcaster\’s type IV and
type VI MAGIC chits he chooses, Day: Each targeted Type IV chit Is
transformed into a Type VIII chit, and each targeted Type VI chit is
transformed into a Type V chit (see Rule 4.6.10c). </item>
        <item>FIERY BLAST (IV/PURPLE), any number of character(s), monster(s)
and/or native(s), Attack: This spell attacks each target like a missile weapon
with a length of 13, and it inflicts Light damage plus three sharpness stars.</item>
        <item>HURRICANE WINDS (IV/PURPLE), one character, monster or native, Fly:
This spell can be cast only in a mountain clearing. It creates a Fly chit with
Tremendous strength and a time number of “1". The target must use this chit
to fly away just before the next encounter step begins; the Fly chit overrules
the target's normal behavior. When this spell is cast on a red-side-up T
monster or its target, the monster immediately drops its target and turns redside-down,
and the target of the spell flies away. When the target flies out of
the clearing, all of his belongings, including his horses, fly and land with him.
The spellcaster chooses which adjacent tile the target flies to. If the target is
a denizen that does not record turns, it lands at the beginning of Daylight, just
before the first attention chit is chosen. Otherwise, the target lands during his
turn, as usual. </item>
        <item>LIGHTNING BOLT (IV/PURPLE), one character, monster or native,
Attack: This spell can be used only in a mountain clearing. It attacks like a
missile weapon with a length of 18, and it inflicts Medium damage plus three
sharpness stars.</item>
        <item>ROOF COLLAPSES (IV/PURPLE), the spellcaster\’s (cave) clearing,
Attack: This spell can be used only in a cave clearing. It automatically attacks
every character, monster and native in the cave clearing, including the
spellcaster. Hidden individuals in the clearing are also attacked, and can play
maneuvers without becoming unhidden. It attacks like a striking weapon with
a length of 18, and it inflicts Heavy damage with no sharpness stars.
Important: This spell always attacks each target in the Smash direction with a
time number of "4", regardless of the chit or card that was used to cast it.</item>
        <item>VIOLENT STORM (IV/PURPLE), the spellcaster\’s hex tile, Day: The
spellcaster rolls the dice and consults the Violent Storm table. The result is
the number of phases each character, hired leader and controlled monster
must cancel when he ends a phase in a woods or mountain clearing in that
tile. He pays this penalty only once per turn, and he can choose which
activities to cancel. He can cancel only those activities that remain in his
current turn - if he loses more activities than he has remaining, the excess
losses are ignored.
* Violent Storm affects only the target tile, and it affects only woods and
mountain clearings that do not contain the Inn, House, Chapel or
Guardhouse (campfires are affected). A character is not affected until he is in
an affected clearing - he is not affected between clearings, in caves (or
buildings), or when he is flying.</item>
        <!-- TYPE V -->
        <item>ABSORB ESSENCE (V/BLACK), one monster, Permanent: This spell can
            be cast on any monster, even if it is controlled or hired. It cannot be cast on a
            character who has been transmorphized into a monster (he would be a
            "character” target, not a monster). This spell transmorphizes the spellcaster
            into the monster he named as target. His items and horses are not
            transmorphized.
            1. The spellcaster and monster become one entity, even when the spell is
            inert. The spellcaster continues to be represented by his character counter,
            but the absorbed monster simply ceases to exist - it is removed from play and
            is put in the spell's spell box, where it remains until the spell ends. The
            monster no longer functions as a monster: any denizens and Attention chits
            assigned to it become unassigned, and it is released from any spells
            bewitching it. It is not killed and cannot regenerate.
            1.1 If the spellcaster is killed the monster is also killed. The killer gets the
            spellcaster's points plus the monster's bounty points, without multiplication,
            and both the spellcaster and the monster count as kills towards the killer's
            daily total.
            1.2 If the spell is broken without killing the spellcaster, the monster instantly
            appears in the spellcaster's clearing.
            2. When the spell is energized, the spellcaster plays dummy chits and uses
            the monster's combat values instead of his own. He must always use the
            combat values that are on the face-up side of the monster's counter. If the
            monster is Medium or Heavy, he can turn it either side up whenever he plays
            a chit (it does not change tactics). If it is Tremendous, it turns red side up only
            when it gets a hit; once it is red side up, he can turn it red side down
            whenever he plays a chit. The counter automatically turns red side down
            when he changes targets, or when his target is killed.
            2.1 If the monster has a head or club, the spellcaster can play it during
            combat as a second attack against his target. Heads and Clubs can be
            played either side up, even when the body is red-side-up.
            2.2 If the monster is a Demon or Imp with red side down, he casts its spell as
            an attack (like a monster, not a character). He cannot change the spell it
            casts. Special: When the spell is energized, the spellcaster can use the
            monster's Magic type to record spells.
            3. If a spellcaster has duplicate Absorb Essence spells, he can absorb one
            monster per spell. As each spell is energized, he transmorphizes into its
            monster (so he will always be transmorphized into the monster that belongs
            to the most recently energized spell). When the spells are energized
            simultaneously, the spellcaster chooses which one transmorphizes him.
            4. When Absorb Essence is cast by an Artifact or Spell Book, the item
            transmorphizes when the spell becomes energized. The character holding
            the item transmorphizes into the monster; if the item is not held by a
            character, the item itself becomes the monster, and it functions like a normal
            monster in all respects. When the monster is killed the spell is broken and the
            item reappears.</item>
        <item>ASK DEMON (V/BLACK), one Demon or Winged Demon, Instant: The
            spellcaster can ask one question of any other player (in the context of the
            game he is asking the Demon, who knows all about the character), and the
            other player must answer truthfully. The question must be answerable by
            yes, no, or a number, it must be about recorded information or one or
            more game pieces and it must be about the present or past - the spellcaster
            cannot ask about ideas or future intentions (except that he can ask about
            Victory Requirements). Question and answer must be kept secret from the
            other players. Note: The spell has no effect on how the Demon fights. </item>
        <item>BROOMSTICK (V/BLACK), one Light character, Fly: This spell creates a
            Fly chit that the target can use to fly. This Fly chit has Light strength and a
            time number of "1". It can be cast only on a target with Light weight. The
            spellcaster controls when this chit is used, but it can be used only when the
            target uses a Light Move chit. Exception: If the spell caster plays this spell on
            himself, he can play the Fly chit directly, without playing a Move chit.
            Example: The Witch King can cast Broomstick on himself and play the Fly
            chit even though he does not own a Light Move chit.
            1. When the target plays a Light Move chit during the encounter step, the
            spellcaster can interrupt his play and force him to use the Fly chit to charge
            or fly away, as the spellcaster chooses. When the target plays a Light Move
            chit to maneuver, when the final maneuvers are revealed the spellcaster can
            invoke the Fly chit. He cannot change the direction of the target maneuver.
            2. When the target starts to do a Fly phase, the spellcaster can invoke the
            Fly chit and allow him to fly. If he does not invoke the Fly chit, the activity is
            cancelled (unless the target has another source of flying strength).
            3. If the target does a Move phase and plays a Light Move chit to carry
            items, then the spellcaster can invoke the Fly chit and force him to Fly to the
            tile he is moving to instead of moving to a particular clearing.
            4. Any time the target uses a Move chit that is stronger than Light, the
            spellcaster can invoke the Fly chit. When this happens, the Fly chit has no
            effect and the spell is broken. </item>
        <item>CURSE (V/GREY), one character, Instant: The spellcaster rolls on the
            Curses table and applies the Curse to the target. See Rule 4.6.8 and the
            Curses table for information on specific Curse results.</item>
        <item>PENTANGLE (V/BLACK), one character, native or monster, CombatThe
            Demon, Winged Demon, and Imp cannot attack the target, all spells and
            Curses that are bewitching him are temporarily nullified, and no new spells
            can go into effect against him. Pentangle stops only those spells that are
            aimed specifically against the target. He is still affected normally by spells
            that are aimed at other targets, such as Roof Collapses. </item>
        <item>POWER OF THE PIT (V/BLACK), one character, native or monster,
Instant: The spellcaster rolls on the Power of the Pit table and applies the
result to the target. See Rule 4.6.8 and the Power of the Pit table for
information on specific Power of the Pit results.</item>
        <!-- TYPE VI -->
        <item>DISSOLVE SPELL (VI/PURPLE), one spell in the spellcaster\’s clearing,
Instant: The target spell must already exist when it Is specified as a target - it
cannot be a spell that is being cast during the current round. When Dissolve
Spell goes into effect, the target spell is broken. Duplicates of the target spell
are not affected. Note: This spell cannot break Curses. </item>
        <item>ENCHANT ARTIFACT (VI/PURPLE), one Artifact or Spell Book that the
spellcaster has active, Permanent: When the spellcaster names his target,
he must also name one of his recorded spells. This spell and its Magic type
are added to the target. The Magic type and Spell can be new or the same as
the artifact already has.
1. Whenever the Enchant Artifact spell is energized, the target contains the
added type and spell in addition to its own type and spell(s). The character
who is holding the target item can read runes to learn the spell, and he can
play the item to cast the spell (which is automatically awakened). He must
specify which Magic type and spell he is using when he plays the item.
2. A new Magic type can also be used to cast Spell cards of the same type
that belong to the item. Example: If Enchant Artifact is used to add Type VII
to the Good Book, the Good Book can be used to cast its Type VII spells.
3. Each Magic type on the target item can be used once per day, so an item
with two Magic types can be used twice per day - once with each Magic type.
Similarly, when one Magic type is committed to a target, the item can still be
played to use the other Magic type.
4. The same item can be enchanted any number of times, adding a new
Magic type and spell with each casting, but each casting ties up one Enchant
Artifact Spell and the chit or card used to cast it.</item>
        <item>MELT INTO MIST (VI/PURPLE), one character, native or monster,
Permanent: This spell transmorphizes the target into mist. His horses and
items are all transmorphized with him. He cannot carry untransmorphized
items while turned into mist.
1. If the target is a character or hired or controlled denizen, he can do only
the Move, Hide and Follow activities. Special: The target can move along
hidden paths and secret passages that he has not discovered. He does not
discover them as he moves.
2. The target is not affected by spells. Any other spells and curses that are
currently bewitching him are nullified, new spells cannot go into effect against
him and he is not affected by spells aimed at other targets (he is immune to
Power of the Pit results, for example). Important: The Melt into Mist spell itself
is not immune to spells. It can be broken while energized (or inert).
3. The target cannot block or be blocked. The target takes no part in combat -
he cannot charge or attack, and he cannot be charged or attacked. If he is a
character, he has a T4 Move chit that he can use only to run away.</item>
        <item>PHANTASM (VI/PURPLE), one character, Day: This spell creates an
ethereal being (or "phantasm") that the target controls.
1. During Birdsong of the next day he puts an unused piece with himself to
represent the phantasm, and he records a separate turn for the phantasm.
The phantasm gets the same number of basic and sunlight phases as other
characters. It can do only the Move, Peer and Enchant activities.
2. The phantasm takes its turn just before the target character, when the
target characters Attention chit is picked, and it does its Peer and Enchant
activities in the clearing it is in. It uses the target character Magic chits to do
the Enchant activity, and it shares his discoveries list; it can use his
discoveries, and he discovers what it discovers, even if they are in different
clearings. If the Phantasm discovers Hidden Enemies, the controlling
character can only see Hidden Enemies if he is in the same clearing as the
Phantasm.
3. The phantasm cannot carry belongings or recorded Gold, it cannot follow
or be followed, it cannot spy or be spied on, it cannot block nor be blocked,
and it does not summon denizens or cause monsters to move.</item>
        <item>TRANSFORM (VI/PURPLE), one character, monster or native,
Permanent: The spellcaster rolls the dice and consults the Transform table,
and the target is transmorphized into the creature (monster or beast)
indicated by the result. Each time he energizes the spell, he is transformed
into the same creature; he does not roll again.
1. All of the recorded Gold and belongings (Including horses) the target has
with him are transmorphized with him.
2. If the target is a character, hired native or controlled monster, he can gain
new recorded Gold and belongings which are not transmorphized. He must
keep his transmorphized Gold and belongings separate from those that are
untransmorphized; when the spell falls inert, he merges the two groups. Note:
If he ends the day in a location where the color magic needed to energize the
spell is supplied automatically, the Transform spell does not fall inert - it
remains energized without a break. </item>
        <item>UNLEASH POWER (VI/PURPLE), any number of the spellcaster\’s Magic
chits that he chooses, Day: Each Magic chit that is specified as a target is
transformed into a "Move/Fight” chit that can be used as both a Move chit
and a Fight chit, but not both at the same time (it can carry items like a Move
chit, and in combat it can be used once per round, as either a Move chit or a
Fight chit). It has the effort asterisks and time number printed on it, and its
time number defines its strength: each chit with a time of 2 or 3 has Light
strength, each chit with a time of 4 has Medium strength, each chit with a
time of 5 has Heavy strength, and each chit with a time of 6 or more has
Tremendous strength. These chits cannot be used as Magic chits while they
are transformed.
1. Unleash Power ignores any changes in time numbers caused by the
Draught of Speed or Garb of Speed; it always uses the time number printed
on the Magic chit to define that chit's strength.
2. When the target has the Belt of Strength active, it overrides Unleash
Power. The Belt of Strength defines the final strength of each Move/Fight
chit. </item>
        <item>WORLD FADES (VI/BLACK), one character, Permanent: If the target
character is unhidden and there are no denizens on his Melee Section at the
end of a round of combat, he rolls on the Hide table. If he hides successfully,
he remains hidden until he is revealed normally (he can hide and be
discovered repeatedly). The target character must also start (or stop) using
Magic Sight when he does the Search activity. See Rule 7.5.7. </item>
        <!-- TYPE VII -->
        <item>CONTROL BATS (VII/any), all of the Bats In the spellcaster clearing,
Day: The spellcaster controls all of the Bats in his clearing. Special: When
this spell is cast by an Artifact or Spell Book, the Bats are controlled by the
character who holds the item. When no character holds the item, the spell is
nullified.</item>
        <item>PEACE WITH NATURE (VII/GOLD), one character, hired leader or
controlled monster, Permanent: This spell prevents Warning and Sound
chits from summoning monsters when the target ends his turn. If the chits are
face down he reveals them as usual but turns the Warning and Sound chits
face down again to show they have not summoned monsters yet (chits are
face up only if they have had the opportunity to summon monsters). The chits
react normally when anyone else ends his turn in the tile, including followers.
This spell does not affect Site chits, Dwellings, Site cards or the Dragon
Essence card, which continue to summon denizens normally, and it does not
affect prowling monsters that are already in the tile, who still move to the
target\'s clearing. Note: If the target is a hired or controlled denizen, he
remains bewitched when he becomes unhired and uncontrolled. </item>
        <item>PREMONITION (VII/GREY), one character, Day: The target character
chooses when he takes his turn during Daylight. He keeps his Attention chit
instead of mixing it with the others, and each time a new chit is about to be
picked he can either preempt and take his turn or pass and let the next chit
be drawn. When no chits are left, he cannot pass - he must take his turn. He
still gets only one turn per day. If this spell is broken before he preempts, his
Attention chit is immediately mixed in with the remaining chits and is picked
normally to determine when he takes his turn. Special: If several characters
can preempt, they must preempt or pass in turn, going clockwise from the
last character to take a turn and skipping anyone who cannot preempt. </item>
        <item>PROTECTION FROM MAGIC (VII/GOLD), one character, Phase: The target
character is protected from spells and curses for one round of combat or one
phase of his turn. He keeps the spell Magic chit to represent its effect, and
he activates it like an item. When he activates it, it nullifies all spells and
curses that are bewitching him, and prevents new spells from being cast on
him; he is still vulnerable to spells aimed at other targets. At the end of the
phase or round, the spell expires. </item>
        <item>SENSE DANGER (VII/PURPLE), one character, Permanent: The target can
record and do an extra Alert phase on his turn.</item>
        <!-- TYPE VIII -->
        <item>BAD LUCK (VIII/any), one character, Permanent: The target character adds
one to his result whenever he uses any table (except where specified in the
rules or table descriptions). </item>
        <item>DEAL WITH GOBLINS (VIII/BLACK), all of the Goblins in the
spellcaster\’s clearing, Day: The spellcaster pacifies the Goblins. To hire
them, he uses the Neutral column of the Meeting Table. Special: When this
spell is cast by an Artifact or Spell Book, the Goblins are pacified by the
character who holds the item. When no character holds the item, the spell is
nullified. </item>
        <item>GUIDE SPIDER OR OCTOPUS (VIII/GREY), one Spider or Octopus, Day:
The spellcaster controls the monster. Special: When this spell is cast by an
Artifact or Spell Book, the monster is controlled by the character who holds
the item. When no character holds the item, the spell is nullified. </item>
        <item>POISON (VIII/GREY), one weapon counter, native counter, Goblin
counter, Ogre counter or Giant\'s club, Day: Add one sharpness star to the
harm the target counter inflicts when it hits. This spell cannot be cast on the
Alchemist\’s Mixture or a Dagger. </item>
        <item>REMEDY (VIII/GREY), one spell or curse in the spellcaster\'s clearing,
Instant: The target spell or curse must already exist when it is specified as a
target - it cannot be a spell that is being cast during the current round. The
target can be one Curse on one character, or one spell. The target spell or
curse is broken. Duplicates of the spell are not affected.</item>
        <item>WHISTLE FOR MONSTERS (VIII/PURPLE), one face-up Sound chit
anywhere on the map, Instant: This spell cannot be cast in a tile that
contains less than six clearings, and it cannot be cast on a chit that is facedown.
If the target chit is not in the spellcaster’s tile, then it is moved to his
tile. If it is already in his tile, then he can move it to any other tile that contains
six clearings. Thereafter, the Sound chit summons monsters to its new tile.</item>

    </string-array>

    <string-array name="spell_short_description">
        <item>Remove all magic demons and imp</item>
        <item>Repair damage, wounds and fatigued</item>
        <item>Cannot attack until attacked</item>
        <item>Get one wish (roll)</item>
        <item>Extra HIDE phase</item>
        <item>Cannot PEER normally in hex</item>
        <item>Do no write move in advance</item>
        <item>MISSILE Attack on each target\n(specify)\L*</item>
        <item>Immediate PEER in any hex</item>
        <item>Change MAGIC II to IV and VIII to III</item>
        <item>Change MOVE L1=1, M1=2, H1=3, T1=4</item>
        <item>Change MAGIC III to II and VII to VI</item>
        <item>Add one to all SEARCH die rolls</item>
        <item>MOVE randomly</item>
        <item>Group becomes FRIENDLY (work on giants and ogres too)</item>
        <item>Extra SEARCH phase</item>
        <item>Extra phase (cave only)</item>
        <item>Change MAGIC IV to VIII and VI to V</item>
        <item>MISSILE Attack on each target\n(specify)\L***</item>
        <item>Must FLY T1 one hex (mountain only)</item>
        <item>MISSILE Attack mountain only\M***</item>
        <item>All attacked SMASH H4 (cave only)</item>
        <item>Roll to see number of phases lost</item>
        <item>Become monster</item>
        <item>Ask question with yes, no or number</item>
        <item>Can FLY L1 in encounter combat and movement</item>
        <item>Gets one curse (roll)</item>
        <item>Not affected by spells, curses, demons or imp</item>
        <item>Roll for Power of the Pit attack</item>
        <item>Cancel Spell</item>
        <item>Add spell and MAGIC chit to artifact</item>
        <item>Can only MOVE t4 (no fight)</item>
        <item>Move unseen searcher (PEER only) can SPELL</item>
        <item>Become Beast (roll for TRANSFORM)</item>
        <item>MOVE/FIGHT 2,3=L, 4=M, 5=H, 6=T</item>
        <item>Roll HIDE each round - Use MAGIC SIGHT</item>
        <item>MOVE and FIGHT with bats</item>
        <item>Not attacked by warning and sound chits</item>
        <item>Choose when you written move is executed</item>
        <item>Immune to spells for one phase</item>
        <item>Extra ALERT phase/turn</item>
        <item>Add one to all die rolls</item>
        <item>Group becomes NEUTRAL (can TRADE/HIRE)</item>
        <item>MOVE and FIGHT with one monster</item>
        <item>Add one sharpness to damage caused by weapon</item>
        <item>Cancels one spell or curse</item>
        <item>Move sound chit to or from your hex</item>
    </string-array>

</resources>